Guide to the Ethnology Collection 1789-2009
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Ethnology Collection
1789-2009
1880-1950
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 1521
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
3 cubic feet 6 document cases, 2 custom boxes
Collection created by the Oregon Historical Society containing printed ephemera related to ethnic groups of all origins, primarily in Oregon and Portland. Includes brochures, cabinet cards, correspondence, financial records, flyers, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, photographs, registration records, relocation records, reports, scrapbook, and transcriptions. Includes materials related to Japanese American relocation in World War II, and the Russian "Old Believer" community in Oregon.
Historical Note
Since its founding in 1898, the Oregon Historical Society has collected ephemera of all kinds, most of it documenting the history of Oregon and the Pacific Northwest. Around the mid-20th century, librarians at the Society began organizing these materials into what became known as "Topical Collections" formed around particular subjects, such as business and education. One such collection, "Ethnology," served as a catch-all for items related to population groups that share common ties of ancestry and culture. Often materials from other collections were separated from the original sources and added to the Ethnology Collection. Although this practice has since been discontinued, some materials are still filed in Ethnology if they come from accessions composed primarily of unrelated ephemera items. "Ethnic groups" are defined as people who are bound together by common ties of ancestry and culture.
Collection created by the Oregon Historical Society containing ephemera related to ethnic groups, primarily in Oregon and Portland. Includes brochures, cabinet cards, correspondence, financial records, flyers, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, photographs, registration records, relocation records, reports, scrapbook, and transcriptions. Includes materials related to Japanese American relocation in World War II, and the Russian "Old Believer" community in Oregon.
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series A: African-American, 1887-2007
Series B: British, 1876-1987
Series C: Chinese, 1882-1987
Series D: German, 1789-1983
Series E: Hawaiian (Kanaka), 1972
Series F: Irish, 1899-1997
Series G: Italian, 1930-1971
Series H: Japanese, 1920-2007
Series I: Jewish, 1869-2007
Series J: Mexican-American, 1972-1998
Series K: Native American, 1926-1992
Series L: Polish, 1922-1976
Series M: Russian, 1759-1983
Series N: Scandinavian, 1921-1987
Series O: Scottish, 1910-2000
Series P: Welsh, circa 1908-1963
Series Q: Various ethnic groups, 1866-2001
The collection is open to the public.
The collection was assembled from a wide variety of sources by the Oregon Historical Society. Provenance can be traced from accession numbers on individual items.
Additional materials are added to the collection from time to time.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Portland (Or.)
African Americans--Oregon; British Americans--Oregon; Chinese--Oregon; Japanese--Oregon; Germans--Oregon; Hawaiians--Oregon; Irish--Oregon; Italians--Oregon; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; Japanese Americans--Oregon.; Jews--Oregon; Mexican Americans--Oregon; Native Americans--Oregon; Old Believers--Oregon; Polish--Oregon; Russians--Oregon; Scandinavians--Oregon; Scottish--Oregon; Welsh--Oregon
Oregon; Portland; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Brochures; Cabinet cards; Clippings; Financial records; Letters (correspondence); Photographs; Printed ephemera; Programs; Scrapbooks; Transcripts
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
Please note that Danish and Swedish are included in the Scandinavian series.
- African-American, 1887-2007; Series A
  - General, 1935-2007 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Atkins, Charles M. 1887-1888 (Box-folder 1/2)
    "Dat's my Dog; Dat's my Cat" paintings on cabinet cards.
  - First annual African-American Athlete Commemorative Banquet, 1990 July 6 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Gates, J. M. (Mrs. Osley J. Gates), 1949-1989 (Box-folder 1/4)
    "Resource Reader" containing information on Osley James "Jim" Gates, former Executive Director of the City Council Commission on Aging in Portland, Oregon, and past Vice-President of the National Council on the Aging. Also includes information on other Gates and McPherson family members.
  - Kappa Alpha Psi Fraternity, circa 1953-1988 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Les Femmes, circa 1962-1988 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Links, Inc., circa 1959-1988 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Oregon Association of Colored Women's Clubs, circa 1953-1954 (Box-folder 1/8)
- British, 1876-1987; Series B
  See also St. Andrews Society, Coll 123. See also individual listings for Irish, Scottish, and Welsh.
  - General, 1876 (Box-folder 1/9)
    Photostat of The Freeman's Oath from City of Gloucester.
  - Associated British Societies, circa 1881-1915 (Box-folder 1/10)
    Includes British Societies of Portland and British Residents of Oregon.
  - British Benevolent Society of Oregon, 1877-1987 (Box-folder 1/11)
    Includes English Speaking Union and British in Oregon.
  - Bundles for Britain, 1941 (Box-folder 1/12)
- Chinese, 1882-1987; Series C
  - General, circa 1882-1992 (Box-folder 1/13)
    Includes 1898 telegram from W.Q. Gresham to Governor Sylvester Pennoyer regarding the Chinese Exclusion Act; letter (ALs) from Chinese ambassador Cheng Tsao Ju to President U.S. Grant regarding appointment of a Chinese consul in Portland, April 17, 1883. Some materials in Chinese language.
  - Account books, 1954 and undated (Box-folder 1/14)
    In Chinese.
  - Account book of Da Tong Guan Company, 1947 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Books (2), undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Chinese Society, 1941 (Box-folder 2/3)
    Chinese Review and Pageant, Portland.
  - Chinese in Portland, circa 1979-1987 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association (Portland, Or.), 1927-1986 (Box-folder 2/5)
    Leah Hing materials formerly occupying folder 2/5 were removed from this collection and added to Coll 393.
  - Leong family, 1931-1935 (Box-folder 2/6)
    Currency exchange receipts.
  - Portland Chinatown renovation, circa 1985 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Registration records, membership application (CACA), and life insurance membership cards, circa 1921-1926 (Box-folder 2/8-2/10)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore letter re: Chinese Relief, 1938 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - "Things Chinese," Fifth Edition, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
    Booklet containing cultural and medicinal essays about the Chinese, with testimonials to the Dr. C. Gee Wo Chinese Medicine Company in Portland, Oregon.
  - Lottery tickets, circa 1900 (Box-folder 3/1)
- German, 1789-1983; Series D
  - General, 1870-1983 (Box-folder 3/2)
    Includes 1870 Saints Day book in German. Additional materials in German.
  - Germans from Russia, 1980 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Journal of Merck, Carl Heinrich, circa 1970 (Box-folder 3/4)
    Includes photocopy of 1789 journal and 1970 correspondence. In German.
- Hawaiian (Kanaka), 1972; Series E
  - Duncan, Janice K., 1972 (Box-folder 3/5)
    Portland State University masters thesis "Minority Without a Champion: The Kanaka Contribution to the Western United States, 1750-1900."
- Irish, 1899-1997; Series F
  Includes materials relating to the All-Ireland Social Club, Portland
  - General, 1899-1997 (Box-folder 3/6)
- Italian, 1930-1971; Series G
  - Columbus Day celebrations, 1930-1971 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Italian Day picnics, 1931-1960 (Box-folder 4/1)
- Japanese, 1920-2007; Series H
  - General, circa 1933-1969 (Box-folder 4/2)
    Includes photocopies of materials relating to Saburo Ikeda and relocation of Japanese-Americans during World War II, 1942-1946.
  - General, circa 1970-2007 (Box-folder 4/3)
    Some materials in Japanese.
  - Relocation
    - General, 1920-1990 (Box-folder 4/4)
      Includes government and university reports.
    - Manzanar Relocation Center, California, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Minidoka, Idaho, 1943 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Tepedino, Therese, undated (Box-folder 4/7)
      Includes documentary script and notes.
  - Scroll with family genealogy, undated (8/1)
  - Yamashita Shipping Company, 1942 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Yasui, Homer, 1973 (Box-folder 4/9)
    Letter from Robert Takaki.
  - Yasui, Ray T., 1971 (Box-folder 4/10)
    Oral history transcription recorded by Barbara Yasui.
- Jewish, 1869-2007; Series I
  - General, circa 1869-1979 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - General, circa 1980-2007 (Box-folder 5/1)
- Mexican-American, 1972-1998; Series J
  - General, 1972-1978 (Box-folder 5/2)
- Native American, 1926-1992; Series K
  For materials relating to American Indians, see Mss 1531, Indians of North America.
  - General, 1926-1992; 2009 (Box-folder 5/3)
    Includes program for the National Conference on Tribal Archives, Portland, 2009
- Polish, 1922-1976; Series L
  - General, 1922-1976 (Box-folder 5/4)
    Some items in Polish.
- Russian, 1759-1983; Series M
  - General, 1759-1975 (Box-folder 5/5)
    Includes 1759 "Ukaz of Her Imperial Majesty, Autocratic Ruler of All the Russias.. ." in Russian, with English translation.
  - Old Believers
    - Bibliography and art exhibit program, undated (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Correspondence and notes, circa 1969-1979 (Box-folder 5/7)
    - History of the Old Believers, 1978 and undated (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Manual for Educators, 1976 (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Partial articles, undated (Box-folder 5/10)
    - Reports, general, 1973 and undated (Box-folder 5/11)
    - Report: "Radical Acculturation Patterns", 1970 (Box-folder 5/12)
    - Sabey, John, undated (Box-folder 5/13)
      Ph.D. dissertation titled "Starovery and School."
    - Smithson, Michael, undated (Box-folder 5/14)
      "of Icons and Motorcycles."
    - Znamenny chants, undated (Box-folder 5/15)
      Some items in Russian.
    - News clippings, circa 1977-1983 (Box-folder 5/16)
- Scandinavian, 1921-1987; Series N
  - General, circa 1944-1987 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Danish, 1921 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Martin, Kent, 1975 (Box-folder 6/3)
    Includes paper titled "Ethnic Identity and the Fishermen of Skamokawa."
  - Swedish Societies of Portland, circa 1890-1929 and undated (Box-folder 6/4)
    Some items in Swedish.
- Scottish, 1910-2000; Series O
  - General, circa 1974-2000 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Brotherhood of St. Andrew, circa 1910-1983 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Highland Games, 1959-1983 (Box-folder 6/7)
- Welsh, circa 1908-1963; Series P
  - General, circa 1908-1963 (Box-folder 6/8)
    Some items in Welsh. See also Cambrian Social Society, Coll 124.
- Various ethnic groups, 1866-2001; Series Q
  - Other ethnicities, 1866-2001 (Box-folder 6/9)
    Includes single items for Basque, Canadian, Czech, French, Greek, Swiss, Turkish, and Vietnamese groups. Some items in French.
  - Citizens for Interracial Understanding, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 7/1)
    Scrapbook donated by Mrs. Osley James Gates.
  - Naturalization and citizenship, circa 1942-1944 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Oregon Pioneer Register questionnaire, undated (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Pacific Northwest Immigration Convention, 1912 (Box-folder 6/12)